<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Scriptural chronicle of Satans incendiaries viz., hard-hearted persecutors and malicious informers with their work, wages, and ends, who were instruments of cruelty against true worshippers / collected by Charles Harriss.</title>
            <author>Harriss, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R336</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13650186</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13650186</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100977</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45695)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100977)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 789:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Scriptural chronicle of Satans incendiaries viz., hard-hearted persecutors and malicious informers with their work, wages, and ends, who were instruments of cruelty against true worshippers / collected by Charles Harriss.</title>
                  <author>Harriss, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devil --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100977:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100977:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Scriptural CHRONICLE OF Satans Incendiaries, VIZ. <hi>Hard-hearted Perſecutors,</hi> AND <hi>Malicious Informers.</hi> With their <hi>Work, Wages,</hi> and <hi>Ends,</hi> who were Inſtruments of Cruelty againſt true Worſhippers.</p>
            <p>Collected by <hi>Charles Harriſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa 33.1.</bibl>
               <p>Wo to thee that ſpoileſt, and thou waſt not ſpiled, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>And Chap. 25.11.—</bibl>
               <p>And he ſhall bring down their Pride, together with the Spoils of their Hands.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matth. 23.32.</bibl>
               <p>Fill ye up then the Meaſure of your Fathers.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Verſe 33.</bibl>
               <p>Ye Serpents, ye Generation of Vipers, how can ye eſcape the Damnation of Hell.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100977:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100977:2"/>
            <head>A Scriptural Chronicle.</head>
            <p>THis may ſerve as a Touch-ſtone for all Perſecutors to be tryed by, who profeſs the holy Scripture to be their Rule; that ſo all may ſee whoſe ſteps they tread in, whoſe work they are doing, and whoſe Rule they walk by; and what is the reward they may expect in the end.</p>
            <p>THe Devil was and is the Maſter of Envy and Murder; and <hi>Cain</hi> was one of his Children, and learned of his father, the Author of wickedneſs, to be a Perſecutor about Religion, and ſlew righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe, his own works were evil, and <hi>Abels</hi> were perfect; and for doing this wicked act of Murder the Lord pronounced him accurſed: And the Curſe ſtill hangs over the heads of all ſuch who walk by <hi>Cains</hi> rule, and tread in his ſteps of Murder about Religion.</p>
            <p>Alſo juſt <hi>Lot</hi> was perſecuted by the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> becauſe he was a Righteous man, and entertained the Angel of God; &amp; although the Meeting was ſo ſmall, that there was but two beſides his own Family, yet the <hi>Sodomites</hi> gathered together both young and old, and beſet his houſe, and endeavoured to break the door, thinking to abuſe or murder Gods Miniſters that were ſent to call <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom;</hi> ſo that people may ſee how the <hi>Sodomites</hi> formerly were unwilling to let one eſcape out of ſin, they would have all to be wicked like themſelves; &amp; when <hi>Lots</hi> love reacht forth to his Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, deſiring them, <hi>to go forth with him &amp; be ſaved,</hi> telling them <hi>how the Judgments of God would come upon them, if they ſtill continued among thoſe wicked people;</hi> and his words ſeemed to them as an idle Tale; but what was the end of thoſe Perſecutors? firſt they were ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with blindneſs (the day of viſitation paſſed over them) &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards were conſumed with Fire &amp; Brimſtone: ſo all thoſe that aſſault righteous mens houſes, and break down their doors to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Servants of God, are ſeen to walk by the <hi>Sodomites</hi> rule.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mael,</hi> he was a Perſecutor, and a Mocker, its ſaid, <hi>His hand was againſt every man, and he was a wilde man;</hi> ſo let all Moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſee what Stock and Birth they are ofsAlſo <hi>Eſau</hi> was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane man, and a Perſecutor, though he was called a Lord, yet
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100977:3"/>he was a rough ſpirited man, as his Stock are at this day, and threatned to kill <hi>Jacob,</hi> the true Worſhipper; and went on in his envy till a day of Repentance was hid from his eyes, and the Sentence was pronounced, <hi>Becauſe of thy violence againſt thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhame ſhall cover thee, and thou ſhalt be cut off forever.</hi> So all you that tread <hi>Eſaus</hi> ſteps, conſider his end, and what your own is like to be.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Pharoah</hi> the King was a wicked Tyrant over the Lord's People; and when the Lord ſent his holy Servants to exhort his People to depart out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and to be ſeparate from thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed <hi>Heathens,</hi> and come forth, and worſhip him in the beauty of Holineſs; then this <hi>Pharaoh</hi> hardened his heart, and made Laws to oppreſs Gods People, and refuſed to give them liberty to obey the Lord, or to have the free exerciſe of their Conſciences towards him; nevertheleſs, in the end we read they did depart, and gave up to anſwer the mind of God; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, then <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Hoſt, turned perſecutors, indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring by violence to hinder them from having their liberty to ſerve the God of their Fathers; but ſtill would have kept them in darkneſs and bondage among the Uncircumciſed, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the inventions and worſhip of the Magitians, and Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and Hirelings of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> but in due time the Lord wrought deliverance for his People, the true Worſhippers; but the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors and falſe Worſhippers the Lord overturned with an overflowing Deſtruction: And certainly their end cannot be happy, who follow the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> rule.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and <hi>Ahab</hi> were wicked Kings, and they ſet up falſe Worſhip, and refuſed to walk in the holy Way of God themſelves, but perſecuted them that walked in it; and when the Prophets of the Lord came in love, and warned and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them for their falſe Worſhips and Wickedneſs; then they, like unwiſe Kings, counted them their Enemies, and perſecuted them: Even one of the Prophets ſpoke to the King, in the time of his Worſhip; ſo that falſe Worſhippers, as they uſe to do now, cryed <hi>Lay hold on him, for he diſturbs me;</hi> but remember that hand that he ſtretched forth againſt the Prophet was wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; and we ſee it was the manner of the true Prophets, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to flatter Kings in their wickedneſs; for when <hi>Ahab</hi> the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100977:3"/>King had taken <hi>Naboths</hi> Free-hold from him, and had cauſed one more righteous then himſelf, to be ſtoned to death; then the good Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> came to him, to whom the King ſaid, <hi>Haſte thou found me out, Oh my ENEMY;</hi> to whom the Prophet an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>I have found thee becauſe thou haſt ſold thy ſelf to work wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, &amp;c.</hi> And becauſe they ſet up falſe Worſhip, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and impriſoned, and killed the Servants of the Lord: Even a curſe came upon them, and their Families; and it was ſaid, <hi>He that dieth of</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>and of</hi> Ahab, <hi>in the City, the Dogs ſhall eat; if in the Fields the Fowls ſhall eat them:</hi> And <hi>Ahab</hi> himſelf was ſlain in his Chariot, and his Blood run out, ſo that when the Chariot was waſhed the Dogs licked his Blood.</p>
            <p>And much more might be ſaid of ſeveral unrighteous Kings; as, <hi>Baaſha, Ahaz, Hoſheas, Manaſſeth, Ammon,</hi> &amp;c. How they ran in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Pride and Hautineſs, and refuſed to walk in the Way of the Lord, but ſet up falſe Worſhip and drew and compelled the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to it, and very often thereby made <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old to ſin; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Lord ſtill ſent his Prophets then to warn them; though for the ſame, the Prophets were perſecuted, and ſtoned, murdered, and counted Deceivers; for which cauſe the Lord brought a heavy Curſe, and ſore Judgments upon thoſe Kings Families, and alſo upon the People that joyned with them in their falſe worſhip.</p>
            <p>Alſo King <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> he perſecuted the Prophet of the Lord, and the Princes, and the falſe Prophets joyned with him, and the Prieſts would have had the Lord's Servant to have been put to death; and they counted him a Mad-man, and ſmote him, and put him in the Stocks, &amp; alſo in Priſons, and a myerie Dungeon: So People may ſee how buſie the Prieſts and falſe Prophets were formerly, and how directly theſe in ourdayes tread in their ſteps; But what was the Wages and End of theſe Perſecutors? Some of them were ſlain with the Sword, others taken Captives, and their Eyes put out, and they bound with Chains, and their Houſes burnt with Fire. This was the Portion of hard-hearted Perſecutors.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Nebuchadnezer</hi> the King was a ſetter up of falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and he granted forth Order to compel all Nations to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100977:4"/>of his Religion, and to bow at his Muſick and Worſhip, or elſe, they muſt be caſt into a Burning Fiery FURNACE; ſo its ſaid, <hi>All the Princes, the Governours, and Captains, and Judges, and Treaſurers, and Councellors, and Sherriffs, and all the Rulers conformed to the Kings worſhip:</hi> But there were three true Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that would not conform; its very like they were called (as ſome are now) ſtubborn Fellows, and Rebels againſt the Kings Laws, and Breakers of the Peace, and will not be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the higher Powers; and its like ſome Hypocrites would be ready to ſay, <hi>You may conform, the thing being impoſed upon you, you ſhall be clear, and the ſin ſhall be charged upon the Impoſers; or you may kneel down to pleaſe the times, and to ſave your ſelves in a way of Chriſtian prudence, and yet have your hearts true to your own Religion,</hi> &amp;c. But theſe true Worſhippers were of a more valiant Spirit, and told the King to his face, they were not carful to anſwer him in this matter (though in other things, as Tribute, Cuſtom, &amp;c. they could) but they gave him to underſtand, he ſhould not be King of their ſouls and conſciences in matters of Worſhip; and they knew their God was able to deliver out of his hand; however they would not turn to be of his religion and worſhip, let him rage and heat his Furnace as hot as he pleaſed: So ye may ſee that falſe worſhip and perſecution ſtill goes together; for he cauſed his Souldiers to caſt them into the burning fiery Furnace; but what was the Wages of this Perſecutor, who ſet up that falſe worſhip? It is ſaid, he was driven from men, and did eat Graſs as an Oz, till his Hair was grown like Eagls Feathers, and his Nails like Birds Claws, to the end he might know the Moſt High ruleth in the Kingdoms of men, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom every ſoul is to be ſubject; for he is the higher Power, and ſouls Biſhop, who hath ſaid, <hi>My Son give me thy Heart:</hi> and again, <hi>I will teach my People my ſelf, and they ſhall not depart from me:</hi> But it might have been well for <hi>Nebuchadnezer</hi> then, and others now, to receive <hi>Daniels</hi> counſel, who ſaid, <hi>O King, break off thy Sins by Righteouſneſs, and thy Iniquity by ſhewing Mercy to the Poor; if it may be a lengthening to thy Tranquility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again we read of <hi>Herod</hi> the King, how ready he was to be a Perſecutor; for no ſooner the Star appeared, and tidings came that our Saviour was born, but he was troubled, and fearing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100977:4"/>that Truth ſhould come up to reign, he ſent forth and ſlew all the Children that were in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and in all the Coaſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of from two years old and under: ſo that People may ſee how buſie the Devil hath been in all Ages, to make uſe of wicked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, to cruſh the very appearance of that which is good; but as for <hi>Herods</hi> Wages, the Lord ſoon cut him off; and there is little queſtion but he had his Portion among Perſecutors and Murderers.</p>
            <p>Again <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Tetrach</hi> being reproved by <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt for all the evil he had done, and for taking another mans Wife; he turned Perſecutor, and put the Prophet in priſon, and after cauſed his head to be cut off, being requeſted by his own unclean Companions; and its like he could ſay to <hi>John</hi> as ſome ſuch do at this day, when they are reproved by the Lords Meſſengers, <hi>Thou ſawcy Fellow, meddle with thy own buſineſs; thou Deceiver and Heretick, we will take a courſe with you ſhortly; what, you would have us live without ſin, and be perfect:</hi> And ſo People may ſee how the Servants of the Lord in all ages have Suffered by proud corrupt men, ſuch as were Enemies of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Again, Did not the chief Prieſts, and Elders, and Captains prove the greateſt Perſecutors our Saviour Chriſt met with? it was the Prieſts then that hunted after him, to have him murdered; And how many times did they bely him, and ſmite him on the face, and ſtoned him and his Followers, and called him Deceiver, and <hi>Belzebub,</hi> and ſaid he had a Devil? and was it not the Prieſts then that fawned upon the <hi>Heathen</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, deſiring them to help them to crucifie Jeſus and ſought out for falſe Witneſſes to prove, as if he had ſpoken Treaſon a-<hi>Caeſar?</hi> and was it not the Prieſts that gave <hi>Judas</hi> money to be gainſt their Informer? And it was the Hirelings that gave the Souldiers money, and taught them to lye, ſaying, <hi>Chriſt was not riſen, but was ſtolen away:</hi> Alſo people may ſee, that thoſe Rulers, viz. <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> that joyned with the Prieſts to put Chriſt to death, they were alſo falſe Worſhippers; ſo ſtill its evident that Blind Zeal, and Falſe Worſhip, and Pride, and Whoredom, and Covetouſneſs, and Prophaneneſs all joyns to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in this work of Perſecution: but what was the Wages.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100977:5"/>that many received? Chriſt told them their Houſe was leſt deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and the Day of their viſitation was over, and called them a Generation of Vipers, ſaying, <hi>How can you eſcape the Damnation of Hell, for ye are of your Father the Devil,</hi> (though you call <hi>Abraham</hi> your Father) for you are found doing the Devils work, like your elder Brother <hi>Cain;</hi> and many woes he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt them, which was fulfilled upon them, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Families, and their Generations, as is manifeſt to this very day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stephen</hi> alſo was perſecuted by the Prieſts and falſe Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and he bore a true Teſtimony againſt them, ſaying, <hi>Ye Stiff-necked, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed in Heart and Ears, ye do alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the holy Spirit, as your Fathers did; which of the Prophets have not your Fathers ſtoned, or perſecuted? and they have ſlain them that ſhewed before-hand of the coming of the Juſt One, of whom ye have now been the Betrayers, and Murderers;</hi> and thoſe wicked men alſo ſtoned holy <hi>Stephen</hi> to death, and caſt him out of the City; terming him a Deceiver, or Blaſphemer: So people may ſee ſuch Prieſts and Profeſſors that reſiſt the holy Spirit, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low an unholy Spirit; they were, and are perſecutors of the Righteous.</p>
            <p>Alſo it was the Prieſts and the Captain of their Temple, and <hi>Sadduces,</hi> that perſecuted the Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> for prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in the Temple; and alſo put them in Priſon, and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened them, commanding them to ſpeak no more in the Name Jeſus; Mark, the Prieſts hated him then by the Name Jeſus, as bad as they now hate him, by the Name Light, in this day of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Appearance.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Herod</hi> the King made it his buſineſs to vex certain of the Church; he killed <hi>James</hi> the brother of <hi>John</hi> with the Sword; and when he ſaw it pleaſed the Prieſts and <hi>Jews,</hi> he proceeded in his work, and took <hi>Peter,</hi> and put him in Priſon, thinking about <hi>Eaſter</hi> time (when the People wanted ſome ſport, and the Prieſts ſome blood to mingle with their Sacrifice and howling Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) then to have brought him forth, to be a Prey to thoſe blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucking Wolves; but it pleaſed the Lord to ſend his Angel, and deliver his Servant out of all their hands: But this <hi>Herod</hi> the Perſecutor was a wicked proud man, and the Angel of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100977:5"/>Lord ſmote him for his wickedneſs, and the Wages he received was to be eaten with Worms. Let all proud blood-thirſty men think of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Again, it was the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> that ſtirred up the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to perſecute <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas,</hi> &amp; expelled them out of the Coaſt of <hi>Antioch;</hi> and alſo it was the Unbelievers that did the like in <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conium;</hi> and when the Apoſtles came to <hi>Lycaonia,</hi> and had preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and many believed their Teſtimony; then thoſe unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> turned Informers, adn went after them, and made an Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roar, and cauſed <hi>Paul</hi> to be ſtoned, and drawn out of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty near dead.</p>
            <p>Again, when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> was as Inſtruments in the hand of God to caſt out a Damſel a ſpirit of divination; then they that had the gain of her Southſaying, ſaw themſelves at a loſs, they, like Prieſts, turned Perſecutors, and cauſed the Apoſtles to be beaten with many ſtripes, and to be put in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but [mark] thoſe men were not led by the true Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to perſecute, but by that curſed ſpirit of Divination and Southſaying; ſo let all ſuch at this day ſee who is their Leader.</p>
            <p>Again, it was the Unbelievers at <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> and lewd Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of the baſer Sort, that ſet the City in an uproar, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted (like the <hi>Sodomites</hi>) the houſe of <hi>Jaſon,</hi> to have brought out the Diſciples to have miſchiefed or murdered them, and they drew <hi>Jaſon</hi> (the man that had the Meeting at his Houſe) and ſeveral Believers, before the Rulers, crying out, theſe that have turned the World upſide down are come hither alſo; we have many in <hi>England</hi> that loves to be called Believers, rather then Perſecutors: but if a Tree may be known by its fruits, let the meek in heart compare and judge.</p>
            <p>Again <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and his Wicked Company, which made Silver Shrines for <hi>Diana,</hi> and were falſe Worſhippers; they alſo perſecuted the true Worſhippers, crying out, <hi>Our Craft is in danger, as alſo our Temple, and Goddeſs, whom all the World worſhippeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again it was Unbelievers, &amp; falſe Worſhippers that ſtirred up the People againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> when they found him in the Temple
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100977:6"/>and they ſet <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on an uproar, and went about to kill him; and the Prieſts and falſe Worſhippers ſaid, he was not fit to live, and they threw duſt into the Air; and the nimble fingered Prieſt commanded <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould be ſmitten on the mouth; and they informed <hi>Feſtus,</hi> and <hi>Foelix,</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> againſt him; and leſt their own ſmooth Tongues ſhould not lye faſt enough, they got, or hired <hi>Tertullus</hi> to be their Informer and Orator againſt <hi>Paul:</hi> Oh they would fain have been ſucking his blood; for he was the worſt Enemy they had, as for ſpoiling their trade, and diſcovering their hypocriſie, and theſe Prieſts were the chief in all his Sufferings and long Impriſonments; and the Apoſtle ſhews who it was that led theſe Prieſts thus to perſecute, for when he wrote to one of the Churches, he ſaith, <hi>He purpoſed to have ſeen them, but at preſent Satan hindred;</hi> ſo we would have all People ſee whoſe work they are doing that perſecutes and priſons the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord; and again, it is written, <hi>The Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon;</hi> and ſo along throughout the Scriptures: And ſince the Apoſtles, through this long night that hath been over People, according to Hiſtory we find good men, and true Worſhippers, have been perſecuted by Blind Wicked men, who were falſe Worſhippers.</p>
            <p>And becauſe many in theſe late dayes makes it their buſineſs to inſence the Rulers, and inform them againſt the Righteous: I have viewed over the holy Scriptures to ſee what root they ſprang from, and whoſe ſteps they tread in.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I find the Devil is called the Accuſer of the Brethren; he alſo informed againſt <hi>Job;</hi> for in thoſe dayes the Sons of God met together, and the Devil was not pleaſed thereat, ſo he endeavoured to accuſe <hi>Job</hi> before the Lord, and the ſtreſs of his words were to render <hi>Job</hi> a Hypocrite, &amp; that he loved his Oxen and Camels, and Sheep, and things of that nature, more then he loved either God or his Religion; and if the Lord would but ſuffer all he had to be taken from him, then he would deny his Religion, and curſe his God to his Face; ſo the Lord gave Satan leave to try what he could do, Then Satan went out from the Preſence of God, (it was a true Saying) for no Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100977:6"/>abides in his Favourable Preſence; ſo then he drummed upon the ſpirits of the <hi>Sabeans</hi> and <hi>Caldeans</hi> [Mark, they were a wicked Stock] and raiſed them up by the Alarum of Hell; ſo they put on their Swords, and came and killed <hi>Jobs</hi> Servants and took away his Cattel, as you may read at large; nevertheleſs <hi>Job</hi> ſtood firm to his Religion: And the Sons of God met the ſecond time, then the old Informer came again to the Meeting, and informed againſt <hi>Job,</hi> ad he had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and deſired a greater penalty might be laid upon him, ſeeing he ſtill retained his integrity, and the Sons of God ſtill kept up their Meeting; ſo Satan deſired he might have leave to touch this Fleſh, and his Bone? you may ſee how Satan loves to cruſh the Righteous to pieces; but the Lord would not commit <hi>Jobs</hi> Life into his hand, only his Fleſh; See what thou canſt do Satan, with thy Stones, and with thy Whips, and with thy Stocks, and ſet thy Children to beat him, and make him ſore from the crown to the foot; and when all was done the Devil proved a falſe Witneſs, and <hi>Job</hi> proved a true Worſhipper, and the Lord bleſſed him, and gave him more Children and Cattel then he had before the time of Perſecution. Wherefore, Oh all ye Sons and Daughters of <hi>Job,</hi> ſtand faſt unto God, and to his Worſhip, and be vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant for the Truth upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Wiched proud <hi>Haman,</hi> alſo he learned of his father to be an Informer againſt Gods peculier People, and told the King <hi>That their Laws differed from his, and therefore it was not meet they ſhould have their liberty;</hi> but he would give the King ten thouſand Tallents of Silver into his Treaſury, if the King would but give way to him to deſtroy in one day all the Lords People; and all this envy roſe in this proud <hi>Haman,</hi> chiefly becauſe good <hi>Mordecai</hi> would not get up an bow (or put off his Hat) to <hi>Haman;</hi> no ſooner had the King granted <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> requeſt, but the Informer commands th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scribes Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and Governours to aid him, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uilds a Gallows, intending it for <hi>Mordecai;</hi> but the Lord l<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the King ſee <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> wickedneſs, and he remembred his People that had no Helper in the Earth; and this Informer was hanged, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100977:7"/>his ten Sons periſhed, and his Eſtate was given to the <hi>Iews,</hi> and thoſe that had thought to have ſpoiled their honeſt Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in the Country; they themſelves became a Spoil; and there periſhed of them above ſeventy five thouſand: Let all ſuch as have a mind of <hi>Hamans</hi> work take notice whoſe RULE they walk by, and what was the Wages of envious Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers.</p>
            <p>Alſo proud painted fac'd <hi>Iezebel,</hi> ſhe was an Informer againſt the true Worſhippers, and would have had all the Lords Prophets to have been ſlain, and ſhe informed the King how he might get Eſtates from his Subjects, by ſetting up falſe Witneſſes, ſo he did follow her counſel; but it ſoon brought a heavy Curſe both upon him and his; and ſo will it do upon all thoſe who after him walk in his ſteps: And as for <hi>Iezebel</hi> the Informer, for her Wages ſhe was thrown out into the Street, and her blood troden out with Horſes, and the Dogs eat her fleſh; and only the Skull, and Feet, and Palms of her Hands were left. Think of this all you Daughters of <hi>Iezabel,</hi> who are decking your ſelves in Pride, and take delight to mock, and ſcorn, and ſpeak evil againſt the Servants of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Amaziah</hi> the Prieſt turned Informer, and told the King, <hi>That</hi> Amos <hi>had conſpired againſt him;</hi> and then charged <hi>Amos</hi> to be gone further from the Kings Chapel and Court, and if he would Propheſie, be gone to another Land, &amp;c. ſee what an Engion of Satan this Prieſts was; but what Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges had he for his news? it was ſaid unto him, <hi>Thy Wife ſhall be an Harlot, and thy Sons and Daughters ſhall fall by the Sword, and thy Land ſhall be divided by line, and thou ſhalt die in a poluted Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, There were ſeveral wicked men turned Informers againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> that man ſo loved of God, and one that was a true Worſhip<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> now thoſe Informers could not find any thing againſt him, as being Diſloyal, or Unfaithful in the Kings buſineſs, therefore they got a Law to diſturb him in his Worſhip, but this Noble man would not creep into a Hole, or ſhut his Windows, but even as at other times, kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100977:7"/>down and prayed, and gave thanks, and worſhipped the God of his Salvation; and as he was ſo doing the Inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers came and took witneſs, and then went and informed the King; it may be they told him that they took <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Notoriouſneſs of the Fact; and only thus, for worſhipping his God, he was caſt into the Lions Den, but the Lord preſerved and delivered him in a wonderful manner; and then King <hi>Darius</hi> commanded that the Informers, with their Wives and Children ſhould be caſt into the Lyons Den; ſo the Lyons had power over them, and broke all their bones to pieces and devoured them; and this was the Wages of theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers.</p>
            <p>There was alſo ſeveral proud wicked men that informed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the three Children, becauſe they would not bow to falſe Worſhip, in a day when it was attended with ſeveral ſorts of Muſick; but you may read in the Prophets how the Lord ſorely puniſhed that wicked ſtock of <hi>Caldeans,</hi> who were falſe Worſhippers, and perſecuted the true Worſhippers; and it was of thoſe alſo, that helped to kill <hi>Jobs</hi> Servants, and fetch away his Cattel, (about Religion) and it is alſo to be obſerved, that thoſe men that caſt the Lord People into the Fire, by the heat thereof they themſelves were conſumed.</p>
            <p>Again it was an old unclean <hi>Woman,</hi> and her proud dance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Daughter that informed againſt <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and deſired his Head; but ſee, <hi>Herod</hi> was unfit to be a Magiſtrate, that could ſwear to give them whatever could be asked; and ſo cut off that great Prophets head to pleaſe one of <hi>Jezabels</hi> Jmps. Oh, how hath the Righteous in all Ages ſuffered by, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch proud, luſtfull, beaſtlike ſpirits, and yet the Devil ſtill taught his Inſtruments in all Ages, to brand the Lords people with names of Deceivers, and Mad-men, and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, and all ſorts of bad names, thereby to render them odious; but the Truth ſhines over the Darkneſs, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the Righteous is alive in renown; but the day is come, and coming, wherein the memorial of the Wicked ſhall rot, and the name of a Perſecutor ſhall ſtink, and be as a Curſe and a Deriſion.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100977:8"/>
            <p>Alſo curſed <hi>Judas</hi> turned Informer, and the Prieſts gave him thirty pieces of Silver to betray, and help them to take <hi>Jeſus:</hi> So they got their Clubs and Staves, and Weapons of Cruelty, and came and took him, that they might Crucifie him: and how can the Diſciples of Chriſt expect but ſuch as <hi>Judas</hi> in theſe days, who have betrayed all good Conſcience, will likewiſe inform againſt them? but what good did the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney do <hi>Judas,</hi> when the horror and torment of Hell ſeized upon him? then he threw down the Silver, and cried, <hi>I have betrayed Innocent Blood;</hi> and being without hope of Mercy, went forth to hang himſelf, and falling headlong he burſt aſunder in the midſt, and all his Bowels guſhed out: Think of this all ye that turn Informers for filthy lucre ſake; and mark whoſe Rule you walk by, and whoſe work you are doing; for its writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (when <hi>Iudas</hi> turned Informer) <hi>then Satan entred him;</hi> ſo Chriſt might well ſay then to <hi>Iudas,</hi> and his Companions, <hi>this is your hour and power of Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might even fill a large Volvme, ſhewing, through all Ages, how it was ſuch as were led by a wrong ſpirit that perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Righteous; <hi>Iohn,</hi> that beloved Diſciple, was baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by wicked men: And thoſe were wicked Inſtruments that mocked the Lords Prophet, ſaying, <hi>Go up thou Bald-head;</hi> ſo the Lord ſent wild Bears and devoured them: And it was wicked men that perſecuted <hi>David,</hi> and curſed him; and it was the Drunkards that made Songs of him, and beat, and ſtoned the Prophets: And it was ſuch wicked men that called the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Deceivers, and Ring-leaders, and Peſtilent Fellows, and movers of Sedition, and Bablers; and when they were filled with the Spirit of Chriſt, ſome accuſed them, as being Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, and Mad-men; and it was the Wicked that often times attempted to ſtone our Saviour, and his Meſſengers, calling him Blaſphemer, and many reproachfull names, as we read at large in the Scriptures of Truth, and yet many that profeſs the Scriptures to be their Rule; and to bear the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, are found directly walking in the ſteps of thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men which the teſtimony of Scripture goes fully againſt; and it was wicked men that ſpoiled the Saints Goods formerly,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100977:8"/>about Religion, and baniſhed them, and ſmote them on the Cheek, and drew them about the Streets, and pulled off their Hair; ſo I hope here is teſtimonies ſufficient concerning Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, to cauſe all ſober underſtanding men and women to conclude with me, that the Root of it is the Father of Envy, and Murder, and Lyes, and that Body, and Branches through which it puts forth it ſelf, what ever their leaves may be for ſhew, yet it is but a wild degenerate Plant, of a ſtrange Vine, as is manifeſt by its Fruit, ſeeing it proves a ſowre Grape, which is to be caſt into the Wine-preſs of the fierce Wrath of the Almighty, who knows how to reſerve the Wicked for that day of puniſhment.</p>
            <p>And I would have the Reader to obſerve how all along in the time of the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ſince to this very day, the chief Inſtruments of Satan in the Work of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution is, and hath been the Prieſts, and falſe Prophets, and Hirelings, with their Biſhops and Popes, and ſuch unwiſe Kings and Rulers, who opened their ears to hearken to their Whiſperings, and Lyes, and Slanders, and murdering coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel againſt the Righteous; and by hearkening to thoſe kind of Evening-Wolves, and helping them to ſuck the Blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus, how hath Kingdoms been ſhaken, and Governments overturned, them and their Families curſed, &amp; ſo periſhed in the hot diſpleaſure of the Lord, and their memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al hath rooted, and ſtinks to this very day, as the Enemies of God, and ſo that which was written in the Second Pſalm hath been, and will be fulfilled, <hi>Why did the Heathen rage, and the People murmur, the Kings and Princes band and aſſemble together againſt the Lord and his Truth,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Let us break their bands, and caſt their cords from us;</hi> but then mark, <hi>He that ſitteth in the Heaven ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have them in diriſion, and ſpeak to them in his Wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure, and cruſh them as with an Iron Scepter, and break them in pieces like a Potters Veſſel;</hi> and ſo this is according to that ſaying, <hi>He rebuketh Kings for the ſake of his People, and commanded them not to touch his Anointed, neither harm his Prophets;</hi> and wo be to them that break this Commandment.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100977:9"/>
            <p> But ſome will ſay, <hi>Ought not every</hi> Chriſtian <hi>to obey the King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſay,</hi> Yes, in all Righteouſneſs (actively) but if any Kings command contrary to God, and make Laws contrary to the royal Law of Love and Righteouſneſs, then the Commands of god, and his Law of Truth is to be kept only, and the other witneſſed againſt (not by Plotting or raiſing Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections) but paſſively, in a Lamb like Spirit, undergoing thoſe Penalties that ſhall be inflicted, until the Lord plead with the Oppreſſor, and avenge his Elect, that cries unto him night and day, and have no Helper in the Earth; and this is according to the Saying of Chriſt, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World, therefore my Servants muſt not fight:</hi> And this is the Faith and Patience of Saints, to ſtand ſtill and ſee the Lords Salvation and Preſervation, whilſt they that are killing with Swords periſh, and are devoured one of another.</p>
            <p>But ſay ſome men, <hi>Ought you not to conform, and be of the ſame Religion that the Governours of the Land are pleaſed to eſtabliſh? And if they make a Law, to compel you thereunto; Are you not Rebels if you do not actively obey, ſeeing we have a Chriſtian King, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which I anſwer,</hi> By this Rule, then I may not know what Religion I muſt be of next; ſeeing the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independants,</hi> and others profeſs themſelves <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and we have ſeen how one gets up after another, and every one ſets up a new kind of Worſhip, and cries, <hi>You muſt obey the higher Power, and bow down to my Faſhion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:</hi> So if I ſhould manifeſt my ſelf as a Cloud carried about with every Tempeſt of mens brains, and fooliſh conceits, and ſuch as can do ſee, I little queſtion; but rather then ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer deeply, they can conform to the <hi>Turks</hi> Alcoron, or in the end wheel about to be <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and worſhip the viſible
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100977:9"/>Sun, Moon, and Stars, or fall down to <hi>Nebuchadnezers</hi> Image, if there be but Muſick, &amp;c. But he that is really a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> will ſtand to the Worſhip that Chriſt ſet up, which is in the Spirit and in the Truth, which is the ſame to day as yeſterday, and will remain when Popiſh Dreams and Inventions of gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy headed men will have an end; for the ſtanding Rule that Chriſt hath appointed for his People to walk by, is not a Maſs-Book, nor the Fragments thereof covered with other names; but it is the Spirit of Truth, which he promiſed ſhould lead and guide them, and that it ſhould abide and remain with them for ever: So here is the unchangeable Way, and Rule, and Worſhip ſet up by him, who is King of Kings; and this is the higher Power, unto who the ſoul is to be ſubject; for its written <hi>All Power in Heaven and Earth is given unto him;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let all proud fleſh tremble before him, and let none think to rob him of his Prerogative leſt they be driven to eat Graſs with <hi>Nebuchadnezer,</hi> and ſo be made to know, there is one will rule in the Kingdoms of men.</p>
            <p>But ſay many People, <hi>What do you think of the preſent proceedings againſt Fanaticks? and do you think it ſafe to ſuffer ſuch great Multitude to meet together, and was it not time to limit them, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which I anſwer,</hi> The greateſt Meetings that I have ſeen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly are at the Play-Houſes, and if there be danger in a Multitude, then to be ſure they ſhould be ſuppreſt; for the Proverb ſaith, <hi>The Wicked run together to do Evil;</hi> but I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſuch Meetings, as are for PLAYS, and ſinging of BALLADS, though in the open Streets, are moſt ſuffered, and rather encreaſed then otherwiſe, together with Bear-bait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Revellings, Race-runnings, and much of that nature, whereby the Lord is daily diſhonoured, and the Earth corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but I hear of no Fines that are levied upon ſuch Meeters nor Houſes, nor upon thoſe open prophane Vaſſals of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who ſpend their whole time in cheating <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ools of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and teaching Youth to be Idle, and Wanton, and Curſe, and Swear, and ſo fit them for Baudy-houſes, and to be Theeves, and ſo in the end to the Gallows.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100977:10"/>
            <p> And as for the late Perſecution in it ſelf, I have no reaſon to believe that it is the Fruit of a right Spirit.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe covetous Biſhops and Prieſts were the chief Founders of it, for their own filthy Lucre ſake, that ſo as Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they might have the whole Trade to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and alſo lord over Gods Heritage.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Many of thoſe that gave life to it, the Nation well knows, had more need to ſit down, and repent in Duſt and Aſhes, and wait to know their own Conſciences waſhed and purged from filthineſs; then go about to ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt them that deſire to enter; and alſo to bring again into bondage ſuch who through Grace have eſcaped the the pollutions of the fleſh that is in the World.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it makes ſad the hearts of the Righteous; but many, that are well known by their Neighbours to be Drunkards, Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Players Swearers, &amp;c. even the worſt of men; its like a Feaſt for them; and hereby an Arrow is put into their hands to make the Righteous their Mark, and their Eſtates a continual Prey; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe wicked Inſtruments bragging what they will be worth in few years; but let them remember <hi>Judas</hi> his End; though for a time it may be ſuffered, as in the dayes of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachi, That the proud, and ſuch as work wickedneſs, and daily tempt God may be ſet up, and counted happy, and yet delivered;</hi> But as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Their Damnation ſlumbreth not; for wo be unto ſuch as go in the Way of</hi> Cain <hi>and</hi> Balaam, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Law of God teacheth a man <hi>To love his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as himſelf, and do as he would be done unto, and every one ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for himſelf:</hi> But I do not believe theſe Rulers, that made this late Act would be ſerved ſo themſelves; as they have appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be done to others; and alſo that one man ſhould ſuffer for another, this is contrary to Gods holy Law; and therefore all Kings, Princes, and Rulers, who deſire and expect their Laws and Commands to be kept, let them be ſure themſelves to keep the Commands of God, and act and walk according to his holy equal Law of Love and Righteouſneſs; and this is the way for a Kings Throne to be eſtabliſhed, and his Family and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to be bleſſed, and to cauſe the hearts of the upright to cleave unto him, and make his dread heavy to the Workers of iniquity.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100977:10"/>
            <p> Laſtly, I obſerve, that Kings and great learned men are very ready to be tempering about Religion, pulling down and ſetting up what pleaſeth their Fancies, but we ſee they are not infallible, but are often times carried away with their own high thoughts, and by lending an ear to ſuch creeping De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, that ſerve not the Lord Jeſus, but their own PURSES and BELLIES; they have many fold more ſet up falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and cauſed People to ſin by compelling them thereunto, according to Hiſtory, then ever yet they were Bringers to the true Worſhip, or themſelves found walking in it; and through their darkneſs have perſecuted and ſlain the Lords Worth yes by many cruel Trials and Tortures, judging and condemning them as Deluders and Deceivers: Wherefore, all high and low, come to Chriſt the Light, that ſo ye may ſee over the darkneſs of mens wayes and worſhips, which are full of Envy, Strife, Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Murder, and every evil Work; and ſo come out of them, into the new and living Way, to the living Worſhip of the true God, which is in the Mountain of Holineſs, where there is no killing nor deſtroying, but are known to be Diſciples of Chriſt, in that they love one another, Chriſt being the Authour and Defender of their Faith, which gives them victory over the World; and preſerves his Church (not by CLUBS, and DRUMS, PIKES and SWORDS, in the hands of Drunkards, and Curſers, and Mockers. &amp;c.) upon the Rock of Life by his own eternal Arm, againſt which the Gates of Hell, the Dragons flood of malice, nor all the hoſts of the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Informers, and Perſecutors ſhall not prevail: Therefore, to the higher Power, ſaith the true Church, be Glory forever.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
